Yu Chen | Curriculum Vitae

Education

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute

Ph.D in Computer Science

GPA: 3.89/4.0

University of Michigan-Dearborn

Exchange student in Computer & Information Science

University of Electronic Science and Technology of China

B.Eng. in Telecommunications Engineering

GPA: 3.98/4.0

Troy, NY, USA

Aug. 2015 - Aug. 2020

Dearborn, MI, USA

Aug 2014 Drg 2014

Aug. 2014 - Dec. 2014

Chengdu, China

SEP. 2011 - Jul. 2015

Research & Work Experience

Graduate Research Assistant, RPI

Advisor: Dr. Mohammed J. Zaki

Al Research Intern, IBM Research

Manager: Dr. Lazaros Polymenakos

Graduate Teaching Assistant, RPI

Troy, NY, USA

May 2017 - Jul. 2020

Yorktown Heights, NY, USA

May 2018 - Aug. 2018

Troy, NY, USA

Aug. 2015 - May 2017

Research Highlights

His research interests lie at the intersection of Machine Learning (Deep Learning), Data Mining, and Natural Language Processing, with a particular emphasis on the fast-growing field of Graph Neural Networks and their applications in various domains. His thesis topic is on designing and developing novel deep learning approaches for question answering and generation from structured and unstructured data. His work has been published in top-ranked conferences including but not limited to NeurIPS, ICML, ICLR, AAAI, IJCAI, NAACL, KDD, ISWC, and AMIA. He was the recipient of the Best Student Paper Award of AAAI DLGMA'20. He is also a co-inventor of 4 filed US patents.

Projects

Personalized Search and Recommendation for Health Empowerment

Troy, NY, USA

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Advisor: Dr. Mohammed J. Zaki

May 2017 - Jul. 2020

Designed and developed a novel knowledge-based Q&A system for personalized food search and recommendation.

Graph Learning for Graph Neural Networks

Troy, NY, USA

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Mentor: Dr. Lingfei Wu

Jun. 2019 - Sep. 2019

Designed and developed a novel iterative deep graph learning method for graph neural networks.

Natural Question Generation

Troy, NY, USA

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Mentor: Dr. Lingfei Wu

Mar. 2019 - May 2019

Designed and developed a reinforcement learning based graph-to-sequence model for natural question generation.

Conversational Machine Comprehension

Troy, NY, USA

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Mentor: Dr. Lingfei Wu

DEC. 2018 - Feb. 2019

Designed and developed a system for conversational machine comprehension via recurrent graph neural networks.

Knowledge Base Question Answering

Troy, NY, USA

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Advisor: Dr. Mohammed J. Zaki SEP. 2017 - MAY 2018 Designed and developed a novel bidirectional attentive memory network for question answering over knowledge

Text Analytics via Topic modeling and Text Representation

Troy, NY, USA

Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Advisor: Dr. Mohammed J. Zaki

Aug. 2016 - Feb. 2017

Designed and developed a novel autoencoder-based system for text analytics via competitive learning.

Honors & Awards

Best Student Paper Award of AAAI DLGMA 2020

AAAI DLGMA 2020 Feb. 2020

Student Travel Award of SIGKDD 2017

ACM SIGKDD Jul. 2017

The First-Class People's Scholarship

The University of Electronic Science and Technology of China 2012 - 2013 & 2013 - 2014

National Scholarship

Ministry of Education of China, Top 1.6 %

2011 - 2012

Skills

Research: Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing, Data Mining

Programming: PYTHON = C/C++ > MATLAB > R = JAVASCRIPT = PHP **Software**: PyTorch, TensorFlow, TensorFlow

Publications

Preprints....

- 1. **Yu Chen**, Ananya Subburathinam, Ching-Hua Chen and Mohammed J. Zaki, Personalized Question Answering over a Large-scale Food Knowledge Graph.
- 2. **Yu Chen**, Lingfei Wu and Mohammed J. Zaki, Toward Subgraph Guided Knowledge Graph Question Generation with Graph Neural Networks.
- 3. **Yu Chen**, Lingfei Wu and Mohammed J. Zaki, Iterative Deep Graph Learning for Graph Neural Networks: Better and Robust Node Embeddings.
- 4. Shangqing Liu, **Yu Chen**, Xiaofei Xie, Jing Kai Siow and Yang Liu, Automatic Code Summarization via Multi-dimensional Semantic Fusing in GNN.

Conference Publications...

- Yu Chen, Ching-Hua Chen and Mohammed J. Zaki, Combining User Preferences and Health Needs in Personalized Food Recommendation. In *Proceedings of the 2020 American Medical Informatics* Association Virtual Annual Symposium (AMIA 2020), Nov. 14-18, 2020.
- 2. **Yu Chen**, Lingfei Wu and Mohammed J. Zaki, GraphFlow: Exploiting Conversation Flow with Graph Neural Networks for Conversational Machine Comprehension. In *Proceedings of the 29th International Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence* (IJCAI 2020), Yokohama, Japan, 2020. Acceptance rate=12.6% (592 out of 4717).
- 3. **Yu Chen**, Lingfei Wu and Mohammed J. Zaki, Reinforcement Learning Based Graph-to-Sequence Model for Natural Question Generation. In *Proceedings of the 8th International Conference on Learning Representations* (ICLR 2020), Apr. 26-30, 2020.
- 4. **Yu Chen**, Lingfei Wu and Mohammed J. Zaki, Deep Iterative and Adaptive Learning for Graph Neural Networks. In *AAAI 2020 Workshop on Deep Learning on Graphs: Methodologies and Applications* (**AAAI DLGMA 2020**), New York, NY, USA, Feb. 7-12, 2020. (Best Student Paper Award).

- Yu Chen, Lingfei Wu and Mohammed J. Zaki. Natural Question Generation with Reinforcement Learning Based Graph-to-Sequence Model. In NeurIPS 2019 workshop on Graph Representation Learning (NeurIPS GRL 2019), Vancouver, BC, Canada, Dec. 8-14, 2019.
- Steven Haussmann, Yu Chen, Oshani Seneviratne, Nidhi Rastogi, James Codella, Ching-Hua Chen, Deborah McGuinness, Mohammed J. Zaki. FoodKG Enabled Q&A Application. In *Proceedings of the* 18th International Semantic Web Conference (ISWC 2019), Auckland, New Zealand, Oct. 26-30, 2019.
- 7. Steven Haussmann, Oshani Seneviratne, **Yu Chen**, Yarden Ne'eman, James Codella, Ching-Hua Chen, Deborah L. McGuinness and Mohammed J. Zaki. FoodKG: A Semantics-Driven Knowledge Graph for Food Recommendation. In *Proceedings of the 18th International Semantic Web Conference* (**ISWC 2019**), Auckland, New Zealand, Oct. 26-30, 2019.
- 8. **Yu Chen**, Lingfei Wu and Mohammed J. Zaki. GraphFlow: Exploiting Conversation Flow with Graph Neural Networks for Conversational Machine Comprehension. In *ICML 2019 Workshop on Learning and Reasoning with Graph-Structured Representations* (**ICML LRG 2019**), Long Beach, CA, USA, Jun. 9-15, 2019.
- Yu Chen, Lingfei Wu and Mohammed J. Zaki. Bidirectional Attentive Memory Networks for Question Answering over Knowledge Bases. In *Proceedings of the 2019 Annual Conference of the North American* Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL-HLT 2019), Minneapolis, MN, USA, Jun. 2-7, 2019. Long Oral Paper.
- Yu Chen, Rhaad M. Rabbani, Aparna Gupta and Mohammed J. Zaki. Comparative Text Analytics via Topic Modeling in Banking. In *Proceedings of the 2017 IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence* (IEEE SSCI 2017), Hawaii, USA, Nov. 27-Dec. 1, 2017.
- Yu Chen and Mohammed J. Zaki. KATE: K-competitive Autoencoder for Text. In Proceedings of the 23rd International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (ACM SIGKDD 2017), Halifax, NS, Canada, Aug. 13-17, 2017. Full Oral Paper. Acceptance rate=8.6% (64 out of 748).
- 12. **Yu Chen**, Hao Chen and Jie Shen. Fast Voxel-based Surface Propagation Method for Outlier Removal. In *Proceedings of the 13th International CAD Conference* (**CAD 2016**), Vancouver, BC, Canada, Jun. 27-29, 2016.

Journal Publications.

 Hao Chen, Yu Chen, Xu Zhang, Baiyuan Li, Xiaoqiang Liu, Xuefei Shi and Jie Shen. A Fast Voxel-based Method for Outlier Removal in Laser Measurement. In *International Journal of Precision Engineering* and Manufacturing (IJPEM), 2019.

Patents

- 1. Lingfei Wu, **Yu Chen**, Mohammed J. Zaki. Method and System for Subgraph Guided Knowledge Graph Question Generation. Filed, Jul. 2020.
- Lingfei Wu, Yu Chen, Mohammed J. Zaki. Method and System for Iterative Deep Graph Learning for Graph Neural Networks. Filed, May 2020.
- 3. Lingfei Wu, **Yu Chen**, Mohammed J. Zaki. Method and System for Natural Question Generation via Reinforcement Learning Based Graph-to-Sequence Model. Filed, Jan. 2020.
- 4. Lingfei Wu, **Yu Chen**, Mohammed J. Zaki. Method and System for Conversational Machine Reading Comprehension via Graph Neural Networks. Filed, Aug. 2019.

Professional Services

Technical Program Committee: EACL 2021, DLG-KDD 2020, EMNLP 2020, ACL 2020, IJCAI 2020, AAAI DLGMA 2020

Journal Reviewer: IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering (TKDE), Data Mining and Knowledge Discovery (DAMI), International Journal of Intelligence Systems (IJIS), ACM Transactions on Knowledge Discovery from Data (TKDD), Journal of Computer Science and Technology (JCST), Artificial Intelligence Review (AIRE)